Donald Baxter MacMillan Collection M118
George J. Mitchell Department of Special Collections & Archives, Bowdoin College Library, Brunswick, Maine 04011
Donald Baxter MacMillan collection
1884-1985, undated
M118
George J. Mitchell Department of Special Collections & Archives, Bowdoin College Library, Brunswick, Maine 04011
31.0 linear feet
Materials relating to Donald Baxter MacMillan's expeditions to arctic regions including diaries; journals and logs, including those used for the Peary North Pole expedition and the Crocker Land expedition; correspondence; writings; and adresses.
MacMillan, Donald Baxter, 1874-1970
Related materials
For related collections at Bowdoin College see: MacMillan "Thebaud" Collection; the Miriam MacMillan Collection; the MacMillan-Snyder letters; the MacMillan-Morse Collection; and the holdings of the Peary-MacMillan Arctic Museum.
Biographical/Historical Note
Donald Baxter MacMillan was born November 10, 1874, in Provincetown, Massachusetts, the younger son of Captain Neil MacMillan and Sarah Gardner MacMillan, a shipbuilder's daughter. After receiving his degree from Bowdoin in 1898, MacMillan served as principal of Levi Hall School in North Gorham, Maine (1898-1900). He later taught at Swarthmore Preparatory School in Swarthmore, Pennsylvania (1900-1903), and at Worcester Academy in Worcester, Massachusetts (1903-1908).
MacMillan's correspondence with Admiral Robert E. Peary (Bowdoin 1877) led to his becoming an assistant to the arctic explorer on his expedition to the North Pole (1908-1909). An accident, however, prevented MacMillan from reaching the pole himself, a goal he never realized except by plane.
Over his lifetime MacMillan would make over thirty expeditions to the far North on the schooner Bowdoin, conducting important work in the fields of botany, ornithology, meteorology, and anthropology. Many of these trips he made with his wife, Miriam Look, whom he married in 1935. Together they led several crews of faculty and students (many from Bowdoin) on expeditions into the arctic between 1935 and 1954.
In addition to his arctic expeditions, MacMillan lectured throughout the United States and wrote several books, including Four Years in the White North (1918), Etah and Beyond (1927), and How Peary Reached the Pole (1934). He also served in the U.S. Navy as Lieutenant (1918-1919), Commander (1941-1945), and Rear Admiral (1954); was Tallman Professor of Anthropology at Bowdoin (1932-1933); and was awarded the F.R.G.S. Special Congressional Medal in 1944. He received honorary degrees from Bowdoin (1918) and Boston University (1937) and was educated at Harvard from 1911-1913. He died on September 7, 1970.
Scope and Content
The collection includes diaries, journals and logs (1902-1961), including those used for the Peary expedition (1908-1909) and the Crocker Land expedition (1913-1915); correspondence; manuscript drafts for Four Years in the White North (1918), How Peary reached the Pole: The Personal Story of His Assistant Donald B. MacMillan (1934), and Green Seas and White Ice (1948); addresses, lectures and articles (1897-1931 and undated); lecture schedules and lists (1924-1960); miscellaneous manuscripts; documents (1839-1969); photographs; and maps and charts. Principal correspondents include Robert E. Peary, Robert M. Cross, Charles Cabot Easton, Alfred H. Fenton, Bela W. Norton, Harry L. Palmer, and Clifton A. Towle.
Sponsor
Digitization of materials related to the Crocker Land Expedition generously funded by the Gladys Krieble Delmas Foundation, 2016.
- Correspondence, 1884-1970, n.d., M118.1; 0.65 linear feet
  Series Description:
  This series contains correspondence 1884-1970, n.d.; a separate run of correspondence from MacMillan to Clifton A. Towle dating 1908-1933, n.d.; biographical data; and descriptions of MacMillan literary, photographic, and documentary material.
  Arrangement:
  Arranged chronologically.
  Access Restrictions:
  No restrictions.
  - Alphabetical and chronological list (incomplete?) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1909 Note placed in bottle by DBM and dropped, from S.S. Roosevelt, Sept. 2, 1909, with reply Mar. 8, 1919. ms and ts. (Box 1, Folder 4a)
  - 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1917-1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1936 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1936 Jun (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1936 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1936 Oct-Dec (includes report of Frederick A. Cook's appointment as an honorary doctor) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 (includes documentation of MacMillan's 28th Arctic expedition) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 Correspondence, plus assorted news clippings and articles (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953 Documentation of the Peary affair: charges, trial information, reports (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 1970- (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Chronological list of Clifton A. Towle correspondence (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - DBM to Clifton A. Towle, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - DBM to C.A. Towle, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - DBM to C.A. Towle, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - DBM to C.A. Towle, 1913-1916 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - DBM to C.A. Towle, 1917-1933 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - DBM to C.A. Towle, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Biographical information within correspondence (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Literary Manuscripts by Donald Baxter MacMillan, 1921-1943, n.d., M118.2; 1.85 linear feet
  This series contains manuscripts and typescripts of books written by MacMillan, including "Four Years in the White North" (1918); "Etah and Beyond" (1927); "How Peary Reached the Pole" (1934); several unpublished works; and several translation dictionaries of Eskimo languages. Some manuscripts are incomplete.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 1-51 ms (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 52-99 ms (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 100-151 ms (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 152-200 ms (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 201-251 ms (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 252-274 ms (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" ms for Ch. 18 and 19 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 1-50 typescript (not published in book form) (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 51-100 ts (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 101-150 ts (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 151-200 ts (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" pp. 201-230 ts (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - "The Bowdoin in Baffin Land" Appendix: Ornithology (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Baffin Land Plants (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Weather Observations, pp. 1-12 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Robinson's Report: 3/15/22-4/17/22 pp.1-10 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Baffin Land Expedition, 1921-1922: Instructions for Scientific Works pp. 1-21 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Baffin Land Expedition, 1921-1922 Memo: July 11, 1921, pp. 1-26 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Cover with manuscript notes "Cruise to Iceland." Narrative of the 1930 voyage of the "Bowdoin" to Iceland, the Eastern coast of Greenland, and Labrador in the wake of the Norseman under Erik the Red. MacMillan wrote this work aboard the vessel (there is no ms. journal or diary for this journey of the "Bowdoin." (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - "Cruise to Iceland" pp. 1-25 ms (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - "Cruise to Iceland" pp. 26-60 ms (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - "Cruise to Iceland" pp. 61-99 ms (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - "Cruise to Iceland" pp. 92-126 ms (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - "Cruise to Iceland" pp. 127-162 ms (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - "Cruise to Iceland" pp. 163-204 ms (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - "Eskimo Language: Greenland" Misc. ms pages (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Eskimo Language: Greenland" Misc. ts pages (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Eskimo Language: Greenland" Binder, ts pages (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Hudson Bay, Baffin Land" Vocabulary: "Abdomen"-"Impossible" ms pages (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Hudson Bay, Baffin Land" Vocabulary: "Impudence"-"Rock" ms pages (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Hudson Bay, Baffin Land" Vocabulary: "Rock"-"Youth" ms pages (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Hudson Bay, Baffin Land" Noun Affixes (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Hudson Bay, Baffin Land" Binder: Vocabulary by Type Category (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Ungava Bay, Baffin Land" Autographed letter from E.J. Peck to Commander MacMillan dated July 7, 1913, with list of Baffin Land Eskimo Words, their English equivalents, and notes on grammatical structure (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Ungava Bay, Baffin Land" General Conversation: "Air"-"Cease" ms (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Ungava Bay, Baffin Land" General Conversation: "Walk"-"Wrong" ms (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Ungava Bay, Baffin Land" General Conversation: "Abandon"-"Come" ts. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Ungava Bay, Baffin Land" General Conversation: "Come"-"Deserted" ts. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Ungava Bay, Baffin Land" General Conversation: "Desire"-"Further" ts. "Eskimo Place Names and Aid to Conversation," (H.P. Miscel, No. 10, 575. Published by the Hydrographic Office, U.S. Navy, 1943) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Eskimo Language: Labrador, Ungava Bay, Baffin Land" Copy of book, ts, 154 pages (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Revised pages for section "Eskimo Place Names Found on Northern Charts" ts, pp. 76 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Revised and corrected pages, 78 p (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Revised and complete edition, ts binder (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Misc. pages "Controversial Eskimo", ts Etah and Beyond... (Boston and New York, Houghton Mifflin, 1927) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Etah and Beyond... ms (incomplete) pp. 67-150 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Etah and Beyond... ms (incomplete) pp. 151-250 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Etah and Beyond... ms pp. 251-300 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Etah and Beyond... ms pp. 301-350 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Etah and Beyond... ms pp. 351-400 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Etah and Beyond... ms pp. 401-450 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Etah and Beyond... ms pp. 451-522 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Etah and Beyond... ms pp. 20-48 for last chapter (1928 London ed.?) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Original typescript for pages 204-361 (incomplete: missing pp. 243-283) "Four Years in the White North" (New York and London, Harper and Brothers, 1918) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - ts, pp. 1-50 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - ts, pp. 51-100 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - ts, pp. 101-181 (incomplete) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - ms and corrected ts, pp. 1-50 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - ms and corrected ts, pp. 51-100 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - ms and corrected ts, pp. 101-150 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - ms and corrected ts, pp. 151-279 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Misc. fragments, 18 p (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Original ts of 1950 revision (incomplete) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - ts for Ch. 11 (later ed.) "How Peary Reached the North Pole: The Personal Story of his Assistant, Donald B. MacMillan" (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1934) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - How Peary Reached the North Pole... ts (first draft) pp. 79-125 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - How Peary Reached the North Pole... ts pp. 126-170 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - How Peary Reached the North Pole... ts pp. 171-225 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - How Peary Reached the North Pole... ts pp. 226-250 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - How Peary Reached the North Pole... ts pp. 251-290 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - How Peary Reached the North Pole... ts pp. 291-325 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - ts pp. 326-350 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - ts pp. 351-[377] (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - misc. ms pages (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Galleys "Kah-Da: Life of a Northern Greenland Eskimo Boy" (Doubleday, Doran & Co., 1930) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - ms fragments (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - typescript (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "The North Pole" (unpublished book; all versions incomplete) ms [102] pp (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "The North Pole" (unpublished book; all versions incomplete) ts [57] pp (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "The North Pole" (unpublished book; all versions incomplete) carbon typescript [71] pp (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "The North Pole" (unpublished book; all versions incomplete) another version, [27] pp (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "The North Pole" (unpublished book; all versions incomplete) another version, ms [6] pp ts [13] pp (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "The North Pole" (unpublished book; all versions incomplete) another version, ms [14] pp ts [12] pp (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "The North Pole" (unpublished book; all versions incomplete) fragments [50] pp (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - notes on DeLong, ms [33] pp, ts [13] pp (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 4 chps. from a children's book, ms [7]pp ts [12]pp (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Literary Manuscripts about MacMillan and the Arctic, 1948-1962, n.d., M118.3; 0.85 linear feet
  This series contains manuscripts and typescripts about MacMillan and the arctic. Included are a biography by Allen Everett; three books written by MacMillan's wife, Miriam Macmillan; and a book on native Greenland language.
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Everett, Allen S., "Arctic Odyssey: The Life of Rear Admiral Donald B. MacMillan" pp. 1-419 (Box 3, Folder 27-31)
  - Everett, Allen S., "Arctic Odyssey: The Life of Rear Admiral Donald B. MacMillan" Galley books (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Everett, Allen S., "Arctic Odyssey: The Life of Rear Admiral Donald B. MacMillan" Book reviews & newsprint (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - MacMillan, Miriam, "Etuk the Eskimo Hunter" Original corrected ts (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
  - MacMillan, Miriam, "Green Seas and White Ice" Original carbon ts (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
  - MacMillan, Miriam, "Kudla and his Polar Bear" First draft, 1953, 86 pp. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - MacMillan, Miriam, "Kudla and his Polar Bear" Second draft, 83 pp. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - MacMillan, Miriam, "Kudla and his Polar Bear" Third draft, *final* (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Rasmussen, Chr., "Gronlandsk Sproglaere, (translated by Lt. D.C. Nutt) pp. 1-161 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Rasmussen, Chr., "Gronlandsk Sproglaere, (translated by Lt. D.C. Nutt) Cover (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Articles and Addresses, 1908-1962, M118.4; 0.9 linear feet
  This series contains manuscripts and typescripts of radio addresses and lectures given by MacMillan. It also contains manuscripts and typescripts for various articles written by MacmIllan. Also included are lecture schedules.
  - "Ah-tuck-ta, My Little Polar Bear," ms/ts (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "Andree's Story" Book review (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "Arctic From the Air" Radio address, ms (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "The Canoe Trip" pp. 396-446 with corrections (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Folder accompanying "The Canoe Trip" (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - "Discovery of America" (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Four Years in the White North" Lecture script (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Four Years in the White North" continued (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - "Greenland" (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - "Hunting Polar Bear with the Polar Eskimo" ms (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - "Hunting Records in the Far North" ms for lecture and article written for possible publication in National Geographic (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - "Hunting Walrus with the Polar Eskimos" ms (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
  - "Iceland" lecture ms/ts with pictures (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "Munjoy Hill Observatory and its History" (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - "North, Far North" lecture given at Bowdoin College, August 27, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "With Peary in the Arctic" notes from lecture with slides (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - "Peary at the Big Land" (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - "Peary goes to Conger" [1897 expedition] (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - "Peary the Indomitable" (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - "Peary: A Leader of Men" (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - "Peary as a Leader" ts (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - "Peary: The Man who Refused to Fail" (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - "Peary" [1906 expedition] (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "The "Poleres" Drift" ms (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - "Polar Eskimos" radio address, ms (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "The Real Value of Arctic Work" radio address [MISSING] (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Removing Crocker Land From the Map" [partial] (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - "Robert E. Peary" (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - "Thanksgiving Dinner at Cape Colombia" radio address (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - "Thanksgiving Dinner in the Far North" radio address (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - "The True Value of Arctic Work" radio address (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - "A Visit to the Polar Eskimos" (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - "Why Go North?" (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - "Why Go North?" radio address Feb. 17, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - "The World's Record" (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Untitled article about Peary's 1908-1909 venture to the North Pole (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Untitled talk given by D.B.M. at Commencement dinner, Bowdoin College, June 20, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Lecture posters (fragile) (Map-case D, Drawer D10)
  - Lecture schedules, 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Lecture schedules, 1925-1928 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lecture schedules; Redpath Bureau, 1959-1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lecture schedules, continued (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lecture schedules, continued (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Partial list of institutions where DBM gave lectures with motion pictures and slide photography (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Commentary on DBM's addresses and lectures (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Diaries and Journals - Originals, 1902-1957, M118.5; 7.5 linear feet
  Related Archival Materials:
  Additional volumes related to the Crocker Land expedition are in the Miriam MacMillan papers (M119), Maruice C. Tanguary papers (M328), and Walter E. Ekblaw papers (M327). Journals from the Crocker Land Expedition have been digitized and are accessible through the links in the finding aid. Digitization of materials related to Crocker Land Expedition funded by the Gladys Krieble Delmas Foundation, 2016.
  This series contains diaries, journals, field notes, log books, and various notebooks from throughout MacMillan's career. This includes journals from the Peary North Pole Expedition of 1908-1909, the Crocker Land Expedition of 1913-1917, and for his various expeditions to Labrador, Greenland, and other Arctic destinations. There are also diaries and journals of other members of MacMillan's expeditions.
  - 1902 Feb 3 - 1904 May 4 diary (no. 1) (Volume 1)
  - [1902] Sep 15 - 2; 1905 Jun 21 - Jul 3; 1908 Jan 10 - May 25; 1937 Jan 9 - Jan 11; 1961 Oct 9 - Oct 16 diary (no. 2) (Volume 2)
  - 1908 Jul 17 - 1909 Oct 2 diary, Peary North Pole Expedition (no. 3) (Volume-folio 3)
  - [1908] [Oct 14] - Oct 30 field diary (no. 4) (Volume 4)
  - [1908] Nov 7 - Dec 13 field diary (no. 5) (Volume 5)
  - [1909] Feb 18 - Mar 25 field diary (no. 6) (Volume 6)
  - [1909] Apr 19 - May 31 field diary: support trip (no. 7) (Volume 7)
  - [1909] Jun 8 - Jul 19 field diary (no. 8) (Volume 8)
  - [1908] Jul 18 - [1909] Sep 5 natural history notes (no. 9) (Volume 9)
  - 1912 Jun 1 - [1912] Sep 19 Diary: Trip in power boat GEORGE BORUP, Boston to North Larador (no. 10) (Volume 10)
  - 1912 Dec 13 - 1913 Feb 24 field notebook: astronomical observations (no. 11) (Volume 11)
  - 1913 Field Notebook: Crocker Land Expedition, list of equipment and supplies, calculations of stellar position (no. 12) (Volume 12)
  - 1913 Field Notebook: ornithology, (no. 13) (Volume 13)
  - 1913 Field Notebook: Crocker Land Expediton, list of food, house equipment, (no. 14) (Volume 14)
  - Field Notebook: Crocker Land Expedition, misc. notes, astronomical observations, Eskimo language, n.d. (no. 15) (Volume 15)
  - 1913-1914 Journal: Crocker Land Expedition, July 2, 1913-Feb. 12, 1914 (no. 16) (Volume 16)
  - 1914-1915 "Journal I": Crocker Land Expedition, Feb. 12, 1914-Mar. 26, 1915 (no. 17) (Volume 17)
  - 1915-1916 "Journal II": Crocker Land Expedition, Mar. 28, 1915-Apr. 21, 1916 (no. 18) (Volume 18)
  - 1916-1917 "Journal III": Crocker Land Expedition, Apr. 12, 1916-Apr. 2, 1917 (no. 19) (Volume 19)
  - 1916 Field Notebook: Crocker Land Expedition, July 12-14, [1916] (no. 20) (Volume 20)
  - 1916-1917 Field Notebook: Crocker Land Expedition, Aug. 29, 1916-May 28, 1917 (no. 21) (Volume 21)
  - 1917 "Journal IV": Crocker Land Expedition, Apr. 3-Aug. 24, 1917 (Volume 22)
  - 1913 Fitzhugh Green's Field Notebook: Crocker Land Expedition, 1913 (no. 23) (Volume 23)
  - 1913-1914 Fitzhugh Green's Field Notebook: Crocker Land Expedition, Sept. 25, [1913]-Feb. 3, 1914 (no. 24) (Volume 24)
  - 1914 Fitzhugh Green's Field Notebook: Crocker Land Expedition, Feb. 7-May 20, 1914 (no. 25) (Volume 25)
  - 1920 Diary: Lamson Hubbard Expedition on S.S. THETIS, July 6-Sept. 16, 1920 (no. 26) (Volume 26)
  - 1921-1922 Diary: Baffin Land Expedition, July 1, 1921-Sept. 10, 1922 (no. 27) (Volume 27)
  - 1922 Field Diary: Baffin Land Expedition, June 17-July 30, 1922 (no. 28) (Volume 28)
  - 1921-1922 Notebook: Baffin Land Expedition, 1921-22 (no. 29) (Volume 29)
  - 1921-1929 Log Book: Schooner BOWDOIN, 1921-29 (no. 30) (Volume-folio 30)
  - 1923-1924 Diary: MacMillan Arctic Expedition 1923-24 to Refuge Harbor, No. Greenland, June 26, 1923-Sept. 29, 1924 (no. 31) (Volume 31)
  - 1923-1924 Field Notebook: MacMillan Arctic Expedition 1923-24, Mar.-July, 1924 (no. 32) (Volume 32)
  - 1925 Diary: Expedition of schooner BOWDOIN and PEARY to Greenland 1925, June 20-Oct. 9, 1925; diary-BOWDOIN voyage to Iceland 1930, June 4-Sept. 15, 1930 (no. 33) (Volume 33)
  - 1926 Diary: Expedition 1926 with BOWDOIN and SACHEM, June 19-Sept. 11, 1926 (no. 34) (Volume 34)
  - 1927-1928 Diary: MacMillan Expedition 1927-28, June 25, 1927-Sept. 7, 1928; diary-MacMillan Expedition 1929, June 22-Sept. 15, 1929 (no. 35) (Volume 35)
  - 1928 Field Notebook: MacMillan Expedition 1928-Apr. 9-Aug. [1928] (no. 36) (Volume 36)
  - Notebook: Schooner BOWDOIN, by Jack Crowell [June 29-Aug.31] (no. 37) (Volume 37)
  - 1931 Diary: MacMillan Expedition 1931-33-July 4-Aug. 31, 1931 (no. 38) (Volume 38)
  - 1934 Log Book: Schooner BOWDOIN-MacMillan Expedition 1934, June 7-Aug. 31, 1934 (no. 39) (Volume 39)
  - 1934 Diary: MacMillan Expedition 1934-Apr. 16-Sept. 2, 1934 (no. 40) (Volume 40)
  - 1934 Notebook: MacMillan Expedition 1934, menus for trip, June 16-Sept. 1, 1934 (no. 41) (Volume 41)
  - 1937 Diary: MacMillan Expedition 1937 in schooner GERTRUDE THEBAUD, June 24-Sept. 3, 1937 (no. 42) (Volume 42)
  - 1938 Log Book: Schooner BOWDOIN-MacMillan Expedition 1938, June 27-Sept. 11, 1938; log of U.S.S. BOWDOIN, Sept. 13-Nov. 5, 1941 (no. 43) (Volume 43)
  - 1938 Diary: MacMillan Expedition 1938, May 15-Sept. 8, 1938 (no. 44) (Volume 44)
  - 1938-1941, 1920 Diary: Expeditions, Oct. 20-25, 1938; Mar. 6-Sept. 12, 1939; June 1, 1940-May 26, 1941; July 6-Aug. 29, 1920 (no. 45) (Volume 45)
  - 1939 Log Book: Schooner BOWDOIN-MacMillan Arctic Expedition 1939, June 24-Sept. 9, 1939 (no. 46) (Volume 46)
  - 1941 Journal: U.S.S. BOWDOIN to west coast of Greenland 1941, June 23-Nov. 20, 1941 (no. 47) (Volume 47)
  - 1942-1945 Diary; Diary-June 14-Sept. 16, 1947 (no. 48) (Volume 48)
  - 1944 Diary: Reconnaissance flights for U.S. Navy, May 26-July 8, 1944 (no. 49) (Volume 49)